WILLIAM KENNEDY PAPERS (MSS132) 1926-2003
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
- Essays and Articles, 1963-1970; 1972; 1978-1998; 2002; Undated; 15; 2.03 cu. ft.
  - "Remedios the Beauty is Alive and Well,"Newsweek Drafts and Final Piece, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "A Sense of Community," Correspondence and Reports, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "A Sense of Community," Essay and Scripts, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "A Sense of Community," Grant Proposal, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "A Sense of Community," Project Updates, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "They Who Became We," Drafts, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "They Who Became We," Final, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Two Civilized Buildings," Drafts and Notes, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1950; 1959-2003; Undated; 16; .6 cu. ft.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains correspondence sent to William Kennedy from fellow authors, journalists, politicians, and members of the film industry. Most notably, the files document his relationships with other well-known writers of American literature, especially his decades-long friendships with mentor Saul Bellow and Hunter S. Thompson. Also included is correspondence with Philip Roth, Joyce Carol Oates, Frank McCourt, Doris Grumbach, John Updike, and more. Materials include letters, greeting cards, post cards, fax transmissions, e-mail and one Western Union mailgram. Nearly all of the other series also include correspondence related to the respective series.
  - Babenco, Hector, 1986; 1993-1994; 2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Banks, Russell, 1988; 1990; 1992; 1994; 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bellow, Saul, 1964-2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Callaghan, Barry, 1989-1990; 1993; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cheever, John, 1968; 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Cuomo, Mario, 1983-1984; 1986-1988; 1990-1991; 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Doctorow, E.L, 1974-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Foote, Shelby, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gaddis, William, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Garcia, Marquez, Gabriel, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ginsberg, Allen, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Grumbach, Doris, 1974; 1977-1994; 1997-2000; 2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Heaney, Seamus, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Heller, Joseph, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Kosinski, Jerzy, 1971-1972; 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mailer, Norman, 1986; 1988; 1991-1992; 1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Malmud, Bernard, 1963; 1966; 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - McCourt, Frank, 1996; 2002 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Merkin, Richard, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Montague, John, 1985-1986; 1988-1990; 1994; 1998; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Morrison, Toni, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Moynihan, Daniel P, 1983-1987; 1993; 1995; 1998 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Nicholson, Jack, 1998; Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Oates, Joyce Carol, 1989; 1992-1995; 1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Percy, Walker, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Pinon, Nelida, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Pinsky, Robert, 1995; 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Proulx, Annie, 1994-1997; 2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Puzo, Mario, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Quinn, Peter, 1984; 1986-1992; 1994-1996; 2002; Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Rabassa, Gregory, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Rooney, Andy, 1983; 1986; 1988; 1990; 1996; 1999 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Roth, Phillip, 1987; 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Rushdie, Salman, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Selby, Huber, Jr, 1984; 1988 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Selzer, Dick, 1990; 1995 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Sendak, Maurice, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Shelton, Ron, 1989; 1995 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Sillitoe, Alan, 1985-1986; 1988-1990; 2002 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Smith, Red, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Stone, Robert, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Styron, William, 1973; 1986; 1988; 1993 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Talese, Gay, 1986-1987; 1989-1992; 1994; 1996; Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Terkel, Studs, 1993; 1999 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Thompson, Hunter S, 1959-1965 (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
  - Thompson, Hunter S, 1966-1971; 1973-1974; 1983; 1996-1997; 2001 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Thompson, Hunter S., Photocopies, 1959-1971; 1973-1974; 1983; 1996-1997; 2001 (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
  - Updike, John, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Vonnegut, Kurt, 1970; 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Warren, Robert Penn, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Wolfe, Tom, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General, 1964; 1990; 1992; 2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Investigative Journalism, 1957-1998; Undated; 17; 2.19 cu. ft.
  This series consists of draft articles, background research materials, memos, notes, magazine and newspaper clippings on a number of subjects that William Kennedy explored and reported upon, especially for his Pulitzer Prize nominated series of features for the Albany Times-Union during the mid-1960s. Those articles included investigations into Albany slums, poverty, housing integration, and racial inequalities. While the initial copy appeared in the 1960s, the files in this series document Kennedy's continued interest and active research of the same topics in subsequent decades. Kennedy used the materials on slums as background for O Albany!. Please note the overall dates for the series are not inclusive.
  - Research Articles on Slums, Civil Rights and Housing, 1957-1988; Undated (Oversized 9, Folder 1)
  - War on Poverty Booklets and Literature, 1959; 1964-1965; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Public Accommodations in Summer Resorts, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Housing, Rehabilitation, 1960-1961; 1965-1966; 1980; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rent Control, Housing Code, Notes, Clips, Correspondence, 1961-1963; 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fair Housing Notes and Literature, 1961-1966; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - State Commissions Brochures, 1962-1963; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Urban Renewal, 1962-1963; 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newsweek Magazine, July 29 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Time Magazine, August 30 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Bombing in Birmingham,"Newsweek, September 30 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "City Within a City," Newspaper Articles, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - School Segregation, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Government Brochures, 1963-1964; Undated (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - The Negro in American History Curriculum Resources, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Research Materials on Housing and Civil Rights, 1963-1966; Undated (Oversized 9, Folder 2)
  - Research Articles on Civil Rights and Housing, 1963-1991 (Oversized 9, Folder 3)
  - Intergroup Relations Booklets and Writings, 1963; 1965; Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Housing Data, 1963; 1965-1966; Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kennedy Real Estate, Poverty, and Slum Articles, 1963; 1965-1966; Undated (Oversized 9, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1963; 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Slum Series and South End Notes, 1963; 1965; 1971; Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Negro and Puerto Rican in American History, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Information About Local Fires, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Proposed Civil Rights Legislation, January 6 1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Time Magazine, March 19 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newsweek Magazine, April 5 1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - State of New York Temporary Commission on Revision of the Penal Law and Criminal Code, Special Report on Capital Punishment, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Commission on Religion and Race Reports, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Post Daily Magazine Articles, "Dark Ghetto" Series, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bill Kennedy "Slum" Articles, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Housing Series" Original Drafts, ca. 1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Poverty War Series" Original Drafts, ca. 1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Slum Series" Original Drafts, ca. 1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Civil Rights Special Report, Button-Kennedy Memos, 1965-1966; Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Including Kennedy Articles on Poverty, Urban Issues, Housing, 1965-1966; Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Slums" Clippings Information, 1965-1967; Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Trinity Institution, Including Kennedy Articles and Notes, 1965-1998; Undated (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - The New Republic, December 3 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Clergy Slum Tour, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Liberator Magazine, Vol. 6, No. 11, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Social Science Fiction in Harlem" Article, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - White House Conference Booklet "To Fulfill These Rights", 1966 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Consumer Problems of the Poor Booklet, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Housing in the City of Albany, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Teachers & Writers Magazine, Vol. 12, No. 3, Arts in Harlem Issues, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Housing, 1980; 1982; 1986-1987; Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - New York Articles of Interest, 1994; Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - American Traveler's Guide to Negro History, Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Negro Interview Series" Original Drafts, Notes and Resume, Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Blaming the Victim, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Biographical, 1969; 1983-2003; Undated; 18; 1.28 cu. ft.
  This series features biographical materials about William Kennedy. The majority of documents are news clippings about his work, book reviews and analysis, profile pieces, interview transcripts, articles featuring Kennedy's insights and comments on literature and the arts, and related correspondence. Of interest are newspaper clips and a program from Kennedy's first play Grand View which debuted at the Capital Repertory Theatre in Albany in 1996. There also is a VHS tape of William Kennedy's Albany which aired on PBS and a file discussing the celebration of the acquisition of this collection by the University at Albany. For articles written by Kennedy see Series 15: Essays and Articles or Series 17: Investigative Journalism.
  - Interviews for "Conversations with William Kennedy", 1969; 1983-1989; 1992-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "An Interview with William Kennedy,"Fiction International, 1983-1986; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Kennedy Book Dust Jackets with Short Biographies, 1984; Undated (Oversized 10, Folder 1)
  - Visting Writers Program, Signed Poster and Reading Series, ca. 1984; ca. 1991; ca. 1995 (Oversized 10, Folder 2)
  - Kennedy Profile in Liberation, 1985 (Oversized 10, Folder 3)
  - "An Interview with William Kennedy,"The Missouri Review, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Journalism Review, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Man Has Legs,"Film Comment, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "William Kennedy: An Albany Aficionado,"Meetings & Conversations, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "William Kennedy: An Interview,"The Recorder, 1985; Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "My High School English Teacher,"Teachers and Writers, 1985-1986; 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "An Interview with William Kennedy," University at Albany Publications, ca. 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - News Clippings, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Public Radio Series: New Year, New Voices in American Literature," A Movable Feast, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Poetry Center, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "William Kennedy: The Singularity of Fiction,"The Yale Vernacular, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Contemporary Writers on Cassette New Letters on the Air, 1989; 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "The Art of Fiction: William Kennedy,"The Paris Review, Edited Pages and Correspondence, 1989; 1991; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Interview of Robert Penn Warren, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Writing! Correspondence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "William Kennedy Interviewed by Tom Smith"The Public Radio Book Show, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "William Kennedy, Scruffy Soul and All,", 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Interview with William Kennedy, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Kennedy Profile in The San Juan Star, 1993 (Oversized 10, Folder 4)
  - William Kennedy's Albany, WETA, ca. 1994 (Video-tape 1)
  - Le Nouvel Observateur and A Day in Albany Profile, 1994-1995 (Oversized 10, Folder 5)
  - "A Conversation with William Kennedy,"Image, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - News Clippings, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Conversations with William Kennedy", 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - "William Kennedy: Past, Passing, and to Come"The Boston Book Review, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Grand View Materials, 1996 (Oversized 10, Folder 6)
  - "Beyond Realism: William Kennedy on the Surreal and the Unconscious, the Religious, the Sublime and the Gonzo"New England Review, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Conversations with William Kennedy," Manuscript, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Lennon Documentary Group, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Interview with Colonie High School Student, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "William Kennedy: Conversations with American Authors", 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "William Kennedy: A Reporter in An Imaginary World"Fiction Writer, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Albany is My Kind of Town"Rough Draft Column, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hemingway, Ernest, A&E Biography, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "Reading Matters,"APME News, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "A Fertile Plain for a Writer,"Hudson Valley Magazine, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "William Kennedy," Writer's Choice.net, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "It's Fiction Not Laurels, That Counts for Kennedy,"Times-Union, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Reverence for History: A Conversation with William Kennedy," New York State Archives, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Prohibition in Upstate New York: Reaction and Reform," Averill Park High School History Club, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Celebration of the Acquisition of the Kennedy Papers, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "William Kennedy Discusses His Characters, His Influences, and His Albany," The Buffalo News, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Times-Union Article, Acquisition of the Kennedy Papers, 2003 (Oversized 10, Folder 7)
- Trip to Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland with President Clinton, 1990; 1993-1996; 1998; Undated; 19; .77 cu. ft.
  In 1995 William Kennedy accompanied President Bill Clinton to Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland as part of an American delegation, following a cease fire between the Irish Republican Army and the Loyalist Military Command in Northern Ireland in 1994. The delegation included elected officials, business, labor, religious, and community leaders and was designed to promote both peace and U.S. investment. This series documents that particular trip, including invitations, arrangements, news clips, maps, travel items, correspondence, and backgrounders. In addition, Kennedy and his wife attended a White House dinner in 1996 given by the Clintons in honor of the President of Ireland, Mary Robinson, and the first State visit by an Irish president in more than 30 years. The invitation and dinner menu and related correspondence also are included.
  - "An Irish Empire; The Time is Right", 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - News Clippings on Ireland, 1993-1995; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photocopy of "Conference on Northern Ireland", 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Statement of Gerry Adams, President of Sinn Fein, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Briefing on Northern Ireland Peace Process, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arrangements for Trip, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brochures, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fact Sheet on Ireland, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Information Brief on the Shannon Region of Ireland, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Invitations and Credentials from Trip to Ireland, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - News Clippings, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - President Clinton's Trip to Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland, Speeches, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Press Releases, Embassy of Ireland, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Springvale Training Facility, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "The Trip of President Clinton to Northern Ireland and Ireland" Briefing Book, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Irish America Magazine, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Shankill (Belfast) Newspapers and Business Backgrounder, 1995; Undated (Oversized 10, Folder 7)
  - Irish Newspaper Coverage of President Clinton's Trip, 1995 (Oversized 10, Folder 8-10)
  - Correspondence, 1995; 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Irish State Dinner, White House Invitations, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Map of Belfast, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)